<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pmn.nz/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pmn.nz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-02T20:57:22+13:00</updated><id>https://pmn.nz/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Panashe’s panache panacea</title><subtitle>Hi, I'm Panashe, a life long learner, computer systems engineer and great wonderer of the world.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">I have no idea</title><link href="https://pmn.nz/productivity/2019/09/12/I-have-no-idea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I have no idea" /><published>2019-09-12T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2019-09-12T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>https://pmn.nz/productivity/2019/09/12/I-have-no-idea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pmn.nz/productivity/2019/09/12/I-have-no-idea/">&lt;p&gt;This website doesn’t have any tracking or analytics set up. I have no idea who’s reading or where they are coming from. I think this is fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By focusing on the process of documenting content and communicating ideas, I get better at it and I’m intrinsically motivated to do more of it. I’ve gained, and continue to gain, a lot of value from the work that other people have put out there and I feel obligated to make some kind of contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently finished reading the book &lt;a href=&quot;../books/#Ultra_Learning&quot; title=&quot;my thoughts on Ultra-learning book&quot;&gt;Ultra-learning&lt;/a&gt; and it ties in brilliantly with my commitment to being a life long learner - I am definelty applying some of the techniques in there. I think in this time, it’s very important to get good at whatever it is you do, not just for your own sake but also to the benefit of others who are direclty or indirectly affected by your work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This website doesn’t have any tracking or analytics set up. I have no idea who’s reading or where they are coming from. I think this is fine.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making small changes</title><link href="https://pmn.nz/productivity/2019/08/18/Making-Small-Changes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making small changes" /><published>2019-08-18T23:40:00+12:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T23:40:00+12:00</updated><id>https://pmn.nz/productivity/2019/08/18/Making%20Small%20Changes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pmn.nz/productivity/2019/08/18/Making-Small-Changes/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just finished reading James Clear’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;, and I found it quite &lt;a href=&quot;../books/#Atomic_Habits&quot; title=&quot;my thoughts on Atomic Habits&quot;&gt;brilliant&lt;/a&gt;.
One of the biggest lessons from the book is the power of making small changes and how they compound over time - it’s articulated beautifully in the book. I’m paraphrasing here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;you get what you repeat – time will magnify it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this idea and it’s one more thing I’m going to be more deliberate about in my work flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote so many notes on this book, it almost felt like I was quoting every sentence! No matter, I will go through the notes and post my full review on &lt;a href=&quot;https://saccader.com&quot;&gt;Saccader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve just finished reading James Clear’s book, Atomic Habits, and I found it quite brilliant. One of the biggest lessons from the book is the power of making small changes and how they compound over time - it’s articulated beautifully in the book. I’m paraphrasing here: you get what you repeat – time will magnify it</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Panashe’s Panache Panacea</title><link href="https://pmn.nz/update/2019/08/04/Panashe's-panache-panacea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Panashe's Panache Panacea" /><published>2019-08-04T23:40:00+12:00</published><updated>2019-08-04T23:40:00+12:00</updated><id>https://pmn.nz/update/2019/08/04/Panashe's-panache-panacea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pmn.nz/update/2019/08/04/Panashe's-panache-panacea/">&lt;p&gt;Well, I’ve decided to spruce things up a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;panashes-panache---panashes-panache-panacea&quot;&gt;Panashe’s panache -&amp;gt; Panashe’s Panache Panacea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m really making this my space. As in a space that’s mine. So I’ve gone further down the rabit hole and added another noun to the title. I’m not sure if and when this train will come to a stop but I’m too far gone now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fails&quot;&gt;Fails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as I like to share what’s worked and all things bright and beautiful, I think it’s important to share my &lt;a href=&quot;../fails&quot;&gt;fails&lt;/a&gt; – there are quite a few of them. I’ve linked them in the side bar and I’ll keep updating the list as I go. The list will continue to grow, no doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;going-dark&quot;&gt;Going dark&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also decided to throw in a new coat of paint on the site that’s slightly darker and easier on the eyes. Hopefully it looks better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Well, I’ve decided to spruce things up a bit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tools as extensions of the mind</title><link href="https://pmn.nz/mind/development/2018/04/24/Tools-as-extensions-of-the-mind/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tools as extensions of the mind" /><published>2018-04-24T13:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2018-04-24T13:00:00+12:00</updated><id>https://pmn.nz/mind/development/2018/04/24/Tools-as-extensions-of-the-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pmn.nz/mind/development/2018/04/24/Tools-as-extensions-of-the-mind/">&lt;p&gt;Philosophers have long speculated that our minds are not just in our brains, they are embodied, that is, our bodies form part of our minds. Our bodies do not just consist of peripheral components that are involved in input and output - they do some processing too. They release chemicals and process signals as well - some of which are processed further or interpreted in the brain to give us complex feelings about things and others that fall below the threshold of consciousness. Shockingly, &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of the processes going on in our bodies fall below this threshold. It gives us the sense and perspective of how consciousness is really just the tip of the iceberg, if that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there’s a theory that was put forward by Andy Clark and David Chalmers and others, that they call &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Supersizing-Mind-Embodiment-Cognitive-Philosophy-ebook/dp/B004MDLRQW/ref=mt_kindle?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&quot;&gt;Extended Mind&lt;/a&gt;, that takes this idea further. This theory says that objects in the external environment can form part of the mind as well - that tools out there can be considered part of our cognitive apparatus. This is fascinating and it ties in nicely with some things I’ve read about lately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, this idea is not new, others have alluded to it and Andy Clark and crew acknowledge this. Richard Dawkins’ idea of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Extended-Phenotype-Oxford-Landmark-Science/dp/0198788916/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8&quot;&gt;Extended Phenotype&lt;/a&gt; comes to mind - although the idea is wholly different from Extended Mind it’s got a familiar ring to it. In Extended Phenotype, Dawkins explores the idea that genetic expression is not limited to just animal bodies but extends to the things they do and make in the environment. Think beavers and their dams and how that affects the environment. The dam is a genetic trait that can alter the environment and it’s subject to natural selection/evolution just like an organ attached to the animal! This trait is controlled by genes that most likely affect the mind of the beaver to make it want to make a dam. Or give one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So back to minds. A study that comes to mind is the one that demonstrated that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/691462&quot;&gt;presence of a mobile phone lowers cognitive abilities&lt;/a&gt; in people. The mere presence of it - not use. This can be explained in terms of the Extended Mind - the brain considers the mobile phone with all it’s capabilities part of its computational space. It knows roughly the kinds of things that the phone is capable of and would rather have it do those tasks while it perhaps drives the sequential steps required to produce the desired outcome. Phones are connected to the internet, to Google and Wikipedia and all, they have calculators and GPS and all sorts of apps that can do a whole lot better than the brain can and at very little cost…to the brain - cost here being in terms of effort/energy/cognitive load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this had me thinking about the tools that we use in our daily lives as part of our minds(!) and whether or not thinking about them as such would change what tools we use and how we use them. I mean, these tools can give us superpowers but they can also reduce our umm… natural cognitive abilities. Like muscles and virtually all the systems of the body - if you don’t use it, you lose it - or more likely it will get a new job in the case of neurons. It makes me think about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learned_helplessness&quot;&gt;learned helplessness theory&lt;/a&gt; due to an over-reliance on the tools we use or perhaps the fact that &lt;a href=&quot;https://fee.org/resources/i-pencil/&quot;&gt;no one really knows how to make anything&lt;/a&gt;. Of course that’s the stuff that progress is built on, competencies on top of competencies. It really does make me think about the tools I use and how I would want things to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m was not deliberate about the ‘what’ and ‘how’ of the tools I use but after considering this, I am starting to think more about it, and so should you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Philosophers have long speculated that our minds are not just in our brains, they are embodied, that is, our bodies form part of our minds. Our bodies do not just consist of peripheral components that are involved in input and output - they do some processing too. They release chemicals and process signals as well - some of which are processed further or interpreted in the brain to give us complex feelings about things and others that fall below the threshold of consciousness. Shockingly, most of the processes going on in our bodies fall below this threshold. It gives us the sense and perspective of how consciousness is really just the tip of the iceberg, if that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Panashe’s panache!</title><link href="https://pmn.nz/2017/06/01/welcome-to-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Panashe's panache!" /><published>2017-06-01T14:35:14+12:00</published><updated>2017-06-01T14:35:14+12:00</updated><id>https://pmn.nz/2017/06/01/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pmn.nz/2017/06/01/welcome-to-jekyll/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;eyes rolling&lt;/em&gt; My name you see… Very well then, I’ll let myself out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">eyes rolling My name you see… Very well then, I’ll let myself out.</summary></entry></feed>